Guide to the Morris Huberland Photograph Collection 1940's - 1950's PR 194
New-York Historical Society
Morris Huberland Photograph Collection
1940's - 1950's
New-York Historical Society
PR 194
1.25 Linear feet (2 boxes)
Consisting of 50 photographs taken by Morris Huberland, the images herein depict various neighborhoods in New York City during the 1940's and 1950's.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Photographs of New York City street life from a similar time period can be found in the John Albok Photograph Collection (PR 001), the Geographic File (PR 020), the Subject File (PR 068), and the Andreas Feininger Collection (PR 207). Images by other Photo League members can be found in the Photographer File (PR50), the Erika Stone Photograph Collection (PR267), and the Rebecca Lepkoff Photograph Collection (PR295).
Biographical Note
Morris Huberland was born in Poland in 1909. His father, a rabbi, immigrated to New York City in 1920 by way of Le Havre. His mother, who departed Bremen in 1924 with Morris and the rest of their family, arrived in Philadelphia before settling in New York City's Lower East Side with her husband shortly thereafter.
Following in his father's footsteps, Morris spent some time studying at rabbinical school, but eventually turned his professional interests toward photography. In 1940, he joined the Photo League, citing Eliot Elisofon's lectures on photojournalism as influential to his artistic approach. From 1943 to 1945, Morris fought in World War II and continued to photograph throughout his service. Upon his return, some of these images were exhibited by the Photo League, and the artist deepened his involvement with the League by serving on its exhibition committee.
Morris continued to exhibit work into the 20th- and 21st-centuries at various New York City institutions, including: the Museum of Modern Art, the International Center of Photography, the Jewish Theological Seminary of America, and the Jewish Museum. Additionally, his photographs often accompanied articles published in The New York Times.
Provenance
Gift of artist, 1982-84; Purchase, 1992.
Scope and Content Note
The photographs within this collection depict the social aspects of New York City street life during and after World War II. Huberland's subjects include children, workers, women, African-Americans, and social gatherings.
The collection is arranged by size and the finding aid is grouped by geographic area. These areas include: Fifth Avenue, Greenwich Village, Harlem, the Upper East and West Sides, and the Lower East Side. Photographs with unidentified locations comprise a separate group.
Titles surrounded by quotes are taken from the back of each photograph, which are handwritten in pencil and pen. A visual description of each photograph appears in brackets following the title.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged by print size, and are further grouped by geographic location.
New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Street life -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 20th century -- Pictorial works.; Photo League.; Photographic prints.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Portraits.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.
- Fifth Avenue
  - "5th Avenue, NYC, 'Easter Sunday'" [Four men, one woman in open car], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - "5th Avenue—Easter Sunday" [African-American family], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Mid-Manhattan—5th Avenue" [woman with large corsage], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - "W. 57 or 59 St., 5th Ave" [Two men and a woman in front of store window], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Greenwich Village
  - "Boy in Halloween costume, Greenwich Village, New York City, 1948" (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Harlem
  - "Harlem, NYC, Chicken Pet" [African-American boy with chicken on a leash], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Harlem" [African-American woman on stoop], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Three women], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Harlem, '40, 'Our Gang'" [Group of African-American boys], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Harlem" [3 children sitting on a grate], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Lower East Side
  - [Boys playing ball in a lot], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "East River area, Lower East Side" [Boys congregating in a lot], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Bowery Mission, NYC" [men standing outside Catholic Worker storefront], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Mid-day Affair, Hester St. Park, NYC [Three women talking in park], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Lower East Side, NYC" [Five African-American boys posing in front of brick wall with graffiti], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Bond Rally, WWII, East Side, NYC, St. Mark's Place" [Group carrying large banner saying 'Freedom Must Win/God Bless Our Boys' with large V], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Cannon [?] Street, NYC, Man and grandchild", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Playing 'Bocce' with Wooden Ball, Houston St., NYC", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "East River Sections" [Laundry on clotheslines], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Lower East Side, mother & son", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Canal St., NYC, 'Diamond Exchange'" [Man looking at ring with loupe], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Canal St. Diamond Exchange" [Two men at jewelry counter], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "East Side, NYC" [Elderly couple sitting on steps, man is wearing a yarmulke], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Montage East Side" [Boys posing in lot, laundry on clotheslines visible], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "East Side Protest Meeting" [Men in suits at police barricade], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "E. 5th Street" [Women and children sitting outside], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Bowery Open Lot, Forties" [African-American man warming hands at outdoor fire], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Lower East Side, N.Y." [Woman and children eating. Jewish family, children in yarmulkes], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "East Side, Willet St., NYC" [Woman vendor on street], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Fulton Market" [Men taking a smoking break outside, one man is African-American], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Boys Smoking, Lower East Side, New York City, 1945" (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Division St., NYC, Lower East Side" [Four boys in the shadow of the Manhattan Bridge], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Canal & Bowery" [Street scene in front of Fabrikant Bros. diamond dealers, El visible at right], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Seltzer Delivery, 96 Columbia Street (east side), ca. 1950/Columbia Street on the Lower East Side", circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
- East Side
  - "3rd Ave. and 83rd St." [View of El], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Park Ave. Uptown" [Boys playing in remains of demolished buildings], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Manhattan, Upper Park Ave." [Boys playing in remains of demolished buildings], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
- West Side
  - "N.Y.C. 1959—'July 4'" [People leaning out of apartment windows; two American flags on fire escape] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Central Park W. 'Challenge'" [Four children in park], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Hell's Kitchen, West Side" [Close-up of boy], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "West Fifties" [Three woman and two babies with stroller outside], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Closed firehouse, Amsterdam Avenue in the 90's, New York City, 1954" [Boys posing in windows of closed firehouse] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Liberty Storage Company, West 64th Street, ca. 1950" [Small-size statue of Liberty on top of building], circa 1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
- Unidentified Locations
  - "NYC, Christmas Shopping" [Close-up of two children], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The War Effort 1942, Bond Drive, 1942, N.Y." [Men, women and children in front of building] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - "New York, Outdoor Meeting" [People clustered around safety zone sign], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Man and woman in front of religious icon store; woman is African-American], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - "New York City, 1941, 'The War Effort', tearing down the 'L'" [Shirtless man carrying piece of steel or iron; photo also says Freedom House Award] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Men in suits and hats standing in schoolyard or playground, possibly playing bocce; laundry visible on clotheslines in background], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)